The next two topics deal with operators,
which help perform calculations and check
for conditions within a block of code.
For the first of these two topics,
the emphasis is learning not so much the operators
themselves but the sequence of execution of these
operators. I will first take you through the list
of operators and their order. After doing that,
the next topic emphasizes what these operators
do for calculations and comparisons within
Python code. The six types of operators and
the order in which they are applied are:
Arithmetic
Containment
Comparison
Identity
Logical
Assignment
Those six types are all listed as exam topics,
both for the order of execution and for how these
operators drive results. There is an order of
operations to follow within each type of operator.
Before we go any further, though, understand this:
parentheses supersede these six operators. Over
the next few videos, we will look at some examples
of how parentheses take priority. So that we can
focus on these operators, I will cover these first
with mostly raw numbers and then incorporate how
these operators help build code for games.
Let’s now look at some code. Let’s look first
at assignments, which set values to variables.
The order of assignments is dependent upon the
order in which they are introduced within code.
Looking at this 131-assignment file, x equals 5,
and y equals 3. Then, we have a print statement
on line 3 to print x and y, which, when I run,
prints 5 and 3. Let’s now look at how these
assignments can be sequenced. I’m going to,
on line 4, add a statement to make y equal x.
There are two principles to note here. First,
because y is being assigned another value later in
the code, it will take this new value over the old
value, three in this case. Secondly, when using
an assignment, the variable on the left side of
the equal sign is always set to the value on the
right. In this case, y is now equal to what x is,
which is five and I will prove that by adding
a print statement on line 5: to print y and
running the code. It is important to understand
the sequence of assignments so that, at any
given time, one can assign the correct value to
a variable and determine the value of a variable.
Getting this process wrong leads to logic errors,
which can take valuable time to locate and fix.